I want to start asking you about Stable.
There's tons of L1s right now out there, tons of Layer 1s.
Do we need another one for Stable Coins in particular?
- That's a great question.
And thanks for having me today, Henry.
For Stable, our mission is very straightforward.
We want to solve the problem in terms
of network congestion and unpredictable gas fees.
Being a Layer 1 allows us to accomplish that mission head on.
Right now, using an example, if you
are running an institution that needs to move $100,000
on to Stable Coin, you're going to transact with that.
And let's say at 2 o'clock, it's about $5
to make that transaction.
But layer it in the day, it's $50 to $60
because of network congestion.
Different markets came online.
And that's a problem for the CFO of that company.
They're not able to predict their costs
and understand what needs to be passed on to the customer.
So what our Layer 1s doing is we use USDT
as our native gas token.
So your gas fees are always predictable.
You know what they're going to be before you transact.
And we added on something of sub-second finality.
With that, you can have that money instantly on the other side
and ready to be moved in a liquid sense,
rather than locking up capital for,
could be, 10 minutes or an hour on other Layer 1.
So I'd say our Layer 1 is solving the problem
of moving money efficiently and effectively.
And when it comes to a predictability,
I agree that there's no other token
than where the gas fees are being calculated in here.
It's actually a new USDT.
But also, from a transaction perspective,
does the price of the cost vary per transaction
or that is actually fixed and stable?
- Sure.
So in peer-to-peer, I think we have two models of this.
In our peer-to-peer sense, it's always going to be gas-free.
So our Layer 1 allows you and I to move money back and forth
with no fee and that same great sub-second finality.
In terms of the institutional side,
if you want to move something,
what we have is something called guaranteed block space.
That's going to be, you can use a subscription service
to guarantee what your rates are going to be,
whether you buy a daily, weekly or monthly pass.
And then if it's on the open market,
there may be a variable fee that comes in,
but it's not going to be the same fees you see now
where you have a non-native token or non-USD token
that has a volatility.
This is always going to be based in USDT.
- So obviously, presume if you're launch stable,
you must be quite bullish on the outlook of stablecoins.
And there's a number of predictions out there
of the market cap, assets will hit two, three million,
three trillion and so on and so forth.
From your perspective, where do you expect,
we'll see very high growth when it comes to stablecoin?
It will be emerging markets, it will be institutional,
it will be to be is there a sector
you want to focus on in particular?
- Yeah, I think there's been a growth across the board.
So obviously we saw, during COVID,
there was a big growth in the emerging markets
where we saw stablecoins become the lifeline
for a lot of individuals to move money across borders
or remit money home.
And then businesses have taken a look at stablecoins
now that regulation's coming to play,
whether it's a Genius Act or other legislations
that have really given that framework and that comfort
that's needed for institutions to use a tool
that they saw was valuable,
but didn't know how they could use it.
So I would say across the board,
I think you're going to see the dollar amount
come in from the institution side,
but you're going to see the transaction numbers
come in from the retail side or the end user side.
- That makes it a healthy balance as well.
And you know, Brian, there's a lot of talks
about financial institutions launching their stablecoins
or the deposit tokens depending on the situation,
especially post-genius in the US.
How do you see that outlook?
Do you believe we'll have two, three dominant players
like USDT, USDC, and others?
Or do you believe we'll have some of these
private financial institutions launch
either their own stablecoins or deposit tokens?
- Sure, I think there's definitely a need
in different aspects of different coins
that come into the market.
An example would be, I think there is a yield token
or something that's providing a unique value
that's not available on, let's say,
the largest player at USDT.
When you have a unique value prop on that token,
it could definitely have its market share
and it could maintain that.
But in terms of the limitless number of tokens,
that's gonna be a market-driven decision.
I can't be the predictor of that,
but I would say at 70% of the market, USDT,
which obviously we have a favor towards
being our native gas token,
I would say that's definitely holding its mark
and it's not looking to slip.
But, you know, some more unique or some more novel ideas
that come into play that actually have a grasp
and can build a following,
I think we'll definitely have a play in the future.
- And do you believe we'll have a US
versus the rest of the world element?
I mean, for example, with USDT, there's USAT
that there is launched into US, under genius,
and there's obviously the international USDT or global one.
How do you see that evolve?
You believe we'll have stable coins
that are focused more solely on the US market
in one global or do you think it'll be all matched together?
- I think it's gonna be a mix.
I think you have different countries
and different jurisdictions building out that framework
and I think that the early adoption of that framework
definitely helps the local players in those markets
build a stable coin that satisfies the needs,
whether it's a domestic market play or an international.
I think cross-border USDT is gonna hold a lot of strength
just because the familiarity with the currency
and also the liquidity.
I think domestic markets, those can survive
and also as they become growing market makers,
they can become a larger player in the industry.
- You mentioned familiarity and liquidity.
Obviously, these are key for stable coin growth.
There's a lot of talks, like putting the crypto aside,
the geopolitics around stable coins, right?
With over 95% if not more of stable coins are dollar based
and China and I was looking at launching its own stable coins
outside of the CBDC, how do you see that playing out?
You still believe we'll have US dollar stable coins
dominate the market for the foreseeable future
or competitors ahead?
- Sure, I mean, using the metrics of currently in play,
it's really hard to lose a 70% lead,
but at the same time, I think there are needs
for different currencies that will grow over time.
And it's obviously when the regulation or the jurisdictions
provide the framework in order to enable that.
So absent framework or absent the rules to follow,
it's hard to get that mass adoption.
So I think as that adoption comes into play,
I think you'll see the growth there.
But right now, I think the US definitely came out farther ahead
than it was previously by putting in such concrete framework
that allowed people to build, as you mentioned, USAT.
And they're able to get that off and running
because they understand what they can do
and how they can grow the business.
- And one last question in 30 seconds.
Obviously, they're stable and obviously something
that you're leading.
There's some other L1s or L2s trying to capture
as markets are plasma being one of them.
How is stable different from some of the others
or trying to build really something bespoke
for a stable coin payments?
- It's a great question.
It's something that I get to talk about a lot.
I say our biggest differentiator is that US TD
is baked in at our core.
So our native gas token provides that comfort
when you're transacting on the stable chain
on how much it's gonna cost
and how long it's gonna take to settle
because we're not adding an extra layer of volatility.
So I think we wanna be user centric
and we wanna be centric to how money moves.
- Love it.
I think we'll have you back at one point
to see if all these predictions that turn out to be true.
That was Brian Mayler, the CEO of Stable.
Thanks Brian for being with us.
- Thanks.